Finding Aid for Philip Power Papers 1976-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Philip Power Papers
1976-1998
Power, Philip H. (Philip Harwick), 1938-
Newspaper publisher, regent of the University of Michigan; collection documents Power's tenure on the University of Michigan Board of Regents, his interest in international freedom of the press, and his involvement with the Michigan Job Training Program.
861040 Aa 2
8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection came to the library in four accessions, 1985, 1987, 1989 and 1999. Periodic additions to this collection are expected. Donor no. 7223.
The collection is open for research.
Philip Harwick Power was born in 1938, the only child of University Microfilms founder Eugene Power and his wife, Ann Arbor activist, Sadye Power. Earning an AB from the University of Michigan in 1960, Power continued to study philosophy, politics, and economics at Oxford University on a Marshall Scholarship, where in 1962 he earned his MA. In 1965, Power bought four unprofitable weekly newspapers, covering the towns of Livonia, Redford, Plymouth and Farmington. This initial investment laid the foundations for established the Suburban Communications Corporation, which publishes more than 60 community newspapers and six shopping guides in the Detroit, Lansing and Cincinnati areas. Power, in 1993, received the Lesher Award, the highest honor in the suburban newspaper area. An unsuccessful candidate for the United States Senate's Democratic nomination in 1978, Power served the state on the Michigan Commission on the Future of Higher Education, and as chairman of the Michigan Job Training Coordinating Council. His career interests have also led him to pursuit politics on a global scale, actively defending the freedom of the press on an intergovernmental stage. After his wife's Sarah Goddard Power's death, Power was appointed regent of the University of Michigan, in June 1987. After completing his appointment in 1990, he was elected statewide to the Board of Regents, where he continued to serve until his defeat in the 1998 election. During a critical period for the university Power served on the board and consequently played a significant role in 1996, with the appointment of Lee Bollinger as President of the University of Michigan. As a publisher and a regent, Power played an active role in advocating of the amendment Open Meetings Act for university presidential searches.
The collection documents Power's tenure on the University of Michigan Board of Regents, his interest in international freedom of the press, and his involvement with the Michigan Job Training Program.
Subjects:
Education, Higher--Michigan.; Journalists--Michigan.; Freedom of the press.; Michigan. Commission to Study Higher Education.; Michigan Job Training Coordinating Council.; Occupational training--Michigan.; Power, Philip H. (Philip Harwick), 1938-; UNESCO.; Universities and colleges--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.
- Biographical Information
  The collection begins with a biographical folder including clippings from Power's 1978 bid for the U.S. Senate nomination.
  - Clippings, etc (Box 1)
- UNESCO: Press Freedom, 1976-1985; 2.5 linear feet
  The UNESCO: Press Freedom files cover the period of 1976 to 1985 and comprise approximately 2.5 linear feet of records. These files are arranged alphabetically under four headings: analysis, documents and speeches, meetings, and organization. This series consists mostly of correspondence, press releases, articles and reports dealing with specific issues regarding UNESCO activities and the role of the mass media in world affairs. There are also some materials pertaining to Sarah Goddard Power and her involvement with UNESCO. The researcher should note that the library has a separate collection of papers for Sarah Goddard Power.
  - Analysis
    - Advertising, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Advertising Age: Philip Power article on UNESCO, December 1980 (Box 1)
    - Background: Debate on the World Information Order, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Harley, William G., 1978-1985 (Box 1)
    - Herald Tribune: Philip Power Op Ed article, June 1981 (Box 1)
    - New York Times: Power article on the World Information Order, September 1980 (Box 1)
    - Power, Philip: Miscellaneous writings, 1981-1984 (Box 1)
    - Press Clips, 1978-1985 (Box 1)
    - Protection of Journalism, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Research, 1977-1983 (Box 1)
    - Tartarian, Roger: Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Transnational Data Flows, 1979-1982 (Box 1)
  - Documents and Speeches
    - Broder, David S., May 15, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Bullen, Dana, November 10, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Homet, Robin, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Human Rights Treaties, 1979 (Box 1)
    - MacBride Report, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Documents, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Power, Philip H., 1979 (Box 1)
  - Meetings
    - Belgrade, 21st General UNESCO conference, 1980; 11 folders (Box 1)
    - Ditchley Foundations Conference, June 1984; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Haig, Alexander, April 24, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Intergovernmental Planning Conference on Communications Development, November 6-9, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Intergovernmental Conference on Communications Development, April 14-21, 1980; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Meetings, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Muskie, Edmund, June 10, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Nairobi, 19th General UNESCO Conference, 1976 (Box 2)
    - New York City Meeting, December 8, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Paris, 20th General UNESCO Conference, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Talloires Meeting, May 15-17, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Talloires II Meeting, September 30-October 2, 1982 (Box 2)
    - University of Georgia, United States National Commission for UNESCO, December 12-15, 1979 (Box 2)
    - University of Pennsylvania, World Communications Conference, May 1980 (Box 2)
    - Washington Communications Conference, November 6-9, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Organizations
    - American Newspaper Publishers Association, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - CEO Project, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Chronicle of International Communication, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Council on Foreign Relations Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - Council on Foreign Relations Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - Council on International Communications and Information, 1980-1982; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Georgetown University, Center for Strategic and International Studies, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Institute of International Education, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Intergovernmental Bureau of Informatics, 1981 (Box 2)
    - International Press Institute, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
    - International Program for the Development of Communication, 1981-1983; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Interpress, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Media Institute, 1981 (Box 3)
    - National News Council, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Non-governmental alternatives to UNESCO, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Seven Springs Center, 1980-1982 (Box 3)
    - Sigma Delta Chi, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Twentieth Century Fund, 1980 (Box 3)
    - United Nations Association, 1981 (Box 3)
    - UNESCO, 1980-1984 (Box 3)
    - United States Congress, Philip Power testimony, July 9, 1980 (Box 3)
    - United States Department of State, 1981-1982; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - United States National Commission for UNESCO, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - World Press Freedom Committee, 1979-1985 (Box 3)
- Michigan Job Training, 1983-1989; 3 linear feet
  The Michigan Job Training series has two subseries: the Job Training Partnership Act and Michigan Job Training Coordinating Council. Materials are arranged alphabetically within each subseries and date from ca. 1983 to 1989. This subseries consists of approximately 3 linear feet of correspondence, articles, and reports circulated while Power chaired the Michigan Job Training Coordinating Council. An addition to this series was received in 1989 and is described separately.
  - Job Training Partnership Act
    - Administration
      - Information Systems, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Andrea Long
      - Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
      - MIS Evaluations and Proposals, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Documents
      - Governor's Coordination and Special Services Plan, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Funding
      - CETA Wind-down Funds, 1983 (Box 3)
      - Governor Set-aside for Education, 1983-1985 (Box 3)
      - Program Year, July 1, 1984 (Box 3)
      - Set-asides, Incentive and Technical, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
      - Title II-A, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
      - Title III, 1983-1984; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Grants Program, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Information Systems
      - Department of Labor Plans, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Institute of Science and Technology, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Interest Groups
      - Handicappers, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
      - Private Sector Caucus, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Vocational Education, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Labor: UAW-Ford, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Legislation
      - Wagner-Peyser Act, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Management Information Systems
      - Arthur Andersen and Co., May 2, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Design, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
      - National Labor Market File, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Objectives
      - Federal Performance Standards, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Office of Job Training
      - Marketing, 1984 (Box 4)
      - Policy Retreat, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Progress Reports, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Organizations
      - Greater Detroit Alliance of Business, 1983 (Box 4)
      - MAETD, 1984 (Box 4)
      - Washtenaw Community College, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Perkins Act, 1986 (Box 4)
    - Policy
      - Lou Ferman, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Overall Policy, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Policy Options, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Private Sector
      - Chrysler Training Information, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Economic Alliance for Michigan, 1983 (Box 4)
      - United Auto Workers, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Programs
      - Private Industry Council, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Projects, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Public Groups
      - Veterans, 1983 (Box 4)
      - WIN, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Reports
      - Westat Report, May 1983 (Box 4)
    - Speeches, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Statistics
      - Comparison Statistics, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Subcommittees
      - Management Information Systems, 1983 (Box 4)
      - MIS Letter 84-5 Issue, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Memberships, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Service Area Instruction Letters, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
      - Title III Economic Development, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Job Training Coordinating Council
    - Committees
      - Committee Structure, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Coordinating Council
      - Official Documents, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence
      - Eugene T. Paslov, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
    - Economic Development
      - High Tech Job Creation, 1985 (Box 4)
      - Mazda Negotiations, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Executive Orders
      - January, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Firmstart Proposal, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Funding
      - Governor's Coordination and Special Services Plan, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - Human Investment Policy Task Force, 1985-1987; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Interest Groups: OIC's, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Joint Programs, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Labor Department
      - Temporary Interim Organization Charts, 1983-1984 (Box 5)
    - Marketing
      - Title III Site Visits, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Meetings, 1984-1989; 20 folders (Box 5)
    - Membership, 1987 (Box 5)
    - MESC Feasibility Study (Box 5)
    - Michigan State Plan for Vocational Education, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Strategic Fund for Human Investment, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Office of Job Training
      - Communication Newsletters, 1984-1985 (Box 5)
      - Goals, May 1984 (Box 5)
      - Mission Statement, September 1984 (Box 5)
      - Proposals for, 1983 (Box 5)
      - Training Policy Advisory Network, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Retreats
      - March, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Ross Group: International Market Competition, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Schedules
      - March, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Speeches, 1983; 1985-1986; 13 folders (Box 6)
    - State Government
      - MESC Operation Plan for Fiscal Year, 1984 (Box 6)
    - Statistics
      - Annual Reports, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Subcommittees
      - MIS-Manpower Services Evaluation System, 1983 (Box 6)
      - Youth Subcommittee, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
    - Title III
      - Economic Development, 1984 (Box 6)
      - Economic Development, 1985 (Box 6)
- Commission to Study Higher Education, 1984
  A third series - Commission to Study Higher Education - consists of administrative records and reports dating from 1984. These files are arranged alphabetically by various sub-headings.
  - General Correspondence (Box 6)
  - Memoranda (Box 6)
  - Minutes (Box 6)
  - Activity Files:
    - Budget (Box 6)
    - Campus Visits (Box 6)
    - Capital Outlay (Box 6)
    - Funding
      - Funding Formulae (Box 6)
      - Funding Levels (Box 6)
      - Funding Taxonomy (Box 6)
    - Letters from Presidents (Box 6)
    - Occupational Supply and Demand Panel (Box 6)
    - Poll of Michigan Citizens re Post-Secondary Education (Box 6)
  - Reports
    - First draft of recommendation to Governor Blanchard, March 1984 (Box 6)
    - Recommendations to Governor Blanchard, July 1984 (Box 6)
    - Final Report (Box 6)
  - Roles and Missions Subcommittee
    - Cuts (Box 6)
    - Funding (Box 6)
    - Meetings (Box 6)
    - West Michigan Regional Reports (Box 6)
    - Work Plan (Box 6)
    - Reports
      - Working draft, March 1984 (Box 6)
      - Draft of Statement, October 1984 (Box 6)
  - Final Statement (Box 6)
- University of Michigan Board of Regents, 1987-1998
  The University of Michigan Board of Regents series is comprised of reports, correspondence, newspaper clippings and meeting minutes. The series strongly details the university's 1996 presidential search and Power's advocacy for the amendment of the Open Meetings Act for university presidential search committees. The series spans Power's entire term from 1987-1998.
  - Affirmative Action Lawsuit, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Affirmative Action Materials, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Architecture, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Athletic Department Correspondence, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Autonomy, 1988-1997 (Box 7)
  - Balinese Masks, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Bollinger, Lee Correspondence, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Campus Planning, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Code of Ethics, circa, 1992-1995 (Box 7)
  - Commencement, circa, 1990-1997 (Box 7)
  - Committee Structure, 1993-1996 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    - 1998 (Box 7)
    - June-December 1997 (Box 7)
    - January-June, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Discrimination, 1988-1989 (Box 7)
  - Diversity, Undated (Box 7)
  - Financial Aid, 1993-1996 (Box 7)
  - Financial Management, 1988-1997 (Box 7)
  - Flint Campus, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - FOIA (Freedom of Information Act), 1998 (Box 7)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Housing, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Inglis House, 1990-1993 (Box 7)
  - Investment Advisory Committee, 1993-1994 (Box 7)
  - Journalism Department, 1995-1996 (Box 7)
  - Labor Unions-International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, 1996-1997 (Box 7)
  - Legal, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Marsh & Webber, 1993-1997 (Box 7)
  - Media Presence, circa, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Medical Center
    - Bylaws, 1996-1997 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1994-1997 (Box 7)
    - Financial, 1996-1997 (Box 7)
    - Future, 1996 (Box 7)
    - History, circa, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Law Firm, 1996 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1987-1997 (Box 7)
    - Rules, 1993-1995 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Community Service Corps,1998 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Daily, 1989-1991 (Box 7)
  - Museum of Art, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Musical Society, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Neal, Homer (Box 7)
    (interim president)
  - News Article Awards, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Open Meetings Act, 1993-1996 (Box 7)
  - Presidential-Historical, 1987-1993 (Box 7)
  - President
    - Open Meetings Act, 1995-1996 (Box 7)
    - Press, 1995-1996 (Box 7)
    - Presidential Search, 1995-1996 (Box 7)
    - Public Hearing, 1995-1996 (Box 7)
  - Royal Shakespeare Company, 1998 (Box 7)
  - SACUA (Senate Advisory Council on University Affairs), 1995-1997 (Box 7)
  - Security, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Sexual Orientation, 1993-1994 (Box 8)
  - State of the University
    - Letters, 1992-1998 (Box 8)
    - Materials, 1996 (Box 8)
    - Responses, 1996 (Box 8)
    - Responses, 1997 (Box 8)
    - Responses, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Strategic Plan, circa, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Student-Regent, no date (Box 8)
  - Technology, 1994-1997 (Box 8)
  - Technology Transfer, 1997 (Box 8)
  - Technology Transfer, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Twenty-first Century, 1991-1992 (Box 8)
  - Undergrad Education, 1992-1995 (Box 8)
  - University Record, 1998 (Box 8)
  - University Speeches, 1997 (Box 8)
  - VCM (Value Centered Management), 1997 (Box 8)
  - Vision 2000, 1993 (Box 8)
  - Women, 1989-1991 (Box 8)
  - WUOM (radio), 1989-1996 (Box 8)
- Marshall Symposium, 1997-1998; 0.5 linear feet
  Although not a regent's official duty, during his term, Power organized and ran the Marshall Symposium entitled "The Information Revolution in Midstream: An Anglo-American Perspective." This series records pertain to the planning of the program as well as the event, itself. Primarily consisting of correspondence, the documents demonstrate the University of Michigan's reputation and role as a global leader in the information technology field. This series spans from the fall of 1997 until 1998.
  - Brochures, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Budget, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Budget/Fundraising, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Donors, 1997 (Box 8)
  - Events, 1997 (Box 8)
  - General Invitations, 1997-1998 (Box 8)
  - Marshall Scholars, 1997-1998 (Box 8)
  - Media, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Meetings, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Participants, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Program, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Program Planning, 1997-1998 (Box 8)
  - Schedule/Agenda, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Transcription, 1998 (Box 8)